Guide to the Fanny Simon Papers TAM.185
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Fanny Simon Papers
1946-1985
TAM.185
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
12.0 linear feet in 12 record cartons
Fanny Simon (1903-1989) was a labor organizer, economist, and socialist. Simon taught at James Monroe High School in Brooklyn and in 1936 helped found the New York Teachers Guild. She helped found the Coalition of Labor Union Women and remained active in the Guild's successor, The United Federation of Teachers, serving on its Women's Rights Committee. The papers contain Simon's clippings and research notes on labor in Latin America, her travel diaries, correspondence, and manuscripts.
Simon, Fanny, 1903-1989
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Federation of Teachers Records (WAG 022)
Historical/Biographical Note
Fanny Simon (1903-1989) was a labor organizer, economist, and socialist. She emigrated to New York from Poland in 1913. After receiving a graduate degree in economics from Columbia University, she became a founder in 1936 of the New York Teachers Guild, and taught at James Monroe High School in Brooklyn, N.Y., retiring in 1963. She remained an activist in the Guild's successor organization, the United Federation of Teachers, serving on its Women's Rights Committee, and was also a founder of the Coalition of Labor Union Women. After her retirement, she traveled throughout Latin America, training labor leaders and wrote the apparently unpublished book-length manuscript "The Labor Movement in Latin America." She was a member of the board of the Workers Defense League, served as the Socialist Party U.S.'s representative in international organizations and forums, and was an associate of Socialist Party head Norman Thomas.
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain Simon's clippings and research notes on labor in Latin America, her travel diaries, correspondence, and manuscripts.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance unknown.
Coalition of Labor Union Women (U.S.).; Socialist Party (U.S.).; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; United Federation of Teachers.; Clippings files.; Diaries.; Jewish socialists |z United States.; Labor movement |z Latin America.; Labor unions |z Latin America.; Research notes.; Women socialists |z United States.; Working class |z Latin America.
- Latin American Educational Organizing, 1955-1967 (Box 1)
- Latin American Educational Organizing; Social Democratic Women, 1946-1971 (Box 2)
- Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; Bilingual Teaching Programs, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
- Latin American Educational Organizing, 1955-1971 (Box 4)
- Latin American Educational Organizing; Social Democratic Women, 1955-1971 (Box 5)
- Notes and Diaries from Latin America, 1940-1958 (Box 6)
- Socialist International, 1970-1978 (Box 7)
- Socialist International, 1972-1979 (Box 8)
- Latin American Educational Organizing, 1963-1967 (Box 9)
- Research Index Cards, undated (Box 10)
- Peace Activism, Not in Our Name (Pledge of Resistance), Subject Files, 1984-2003 (Box 11)
- Latin American Organizing, 1958-1978 (Box 12)